You must have heard of
Herman Hollerith or of his work.
Sure, of course!
Hollerith was born 1860 in America
as son of German emigrants
graduated there as
a mining engineer
and started looking
at statistics early on.
For example, in the 1880 census:
The lot of manual work when
evaluating the questionnaires
with the help of tally
sheets made him thoughtful.
Couldn't machines help to reduce the
almost ten-year evaluation period?
A key issue was data collection
what he was looking
for a good medium for
that was suitable for
subsequent machine processing.
On a trip he watched how
the conductor with pliers
on the ticket
through perforations
recorded various
characteristics of the passengers.
For example,
gender or skin color.
This finally gave him an idea:
The principle could
also be used for statistics
and save the necessary attributes
with the help of holes in the paper.
The snap with the pliers
was very exhausting
and also quite imprecise.
That's why he decided to build a
punch which is called
the pantograph.
The punch card is
inserted into the pantograph
and by driving back and
forth to the positions
that represent the desired data
perforations are then made.
I am now randomly
punching some holes
and you see here twelve
hole positions
and horizontally 20 hole positions.
OK!
Hollerith has opted
for a punch card format
with twelve rows and 20 columns.
In the following
demo, a total of four
hole positions are used for diseases
namely for measles,
tuberculosis, diphtheria and flu.
There are also two hole positions for
the male and female characteristics.
In the following we use
the two cards "MM" for
measles male and "DiW"
for diphtheria female.
Now the card is sensed! And another
one! Oh man, measles epidemic!
You can see here
counters for measles
male, tuberculosis,
diphtheria and flu.
And the same for women: Measles
female, tuberculosis,
diphtheria and flu. Aha!
The base plate of the reader
device has for all available attributes
contacts, e.g. for measles,
diphtheria, male and female.
The contacts are electrically
connected to the appropriate counters and
can be logically
combinded using relays.
The reader device has
spring-loaded pins, which
are also connected
to the counters.
If you insert the punch card and then
press down the lever for sensing,
will be where are holes are located
the circuit be closed and
the counter is increased by one.
Wherever there are no
holes, there is no current
and thus the counters
are not switched on.
Then we still have to
process the other person's data
that's diphtheria female.
And if I
press the reading
station, then you see
that counter seven
jumps by plus one.
Hollerith quickly
realized that
sorting the cards
is an important step.
Parallel to the card's sensing
and the movement of the counters
in the sorting box flap one opens
for storing the male measles card.
And we can demonstrate
the same with female diphtheria
then compartment seven opens.
Now that all the
work is done, you can
take the punch cards
from the sorting compartments
and here come the female
cards out and here come the
male cards out. Now if you
want to analyze, where most
measles cases occur, then I
can only take the measles cards
to on another machine
that we
don't have here now, but evaluate
according to this scheme.
That means you now have a
stack of male measles, for example
with other attributes like age
for example. Exactly!
That means we have pre-sorted
for "male measles"
and with a second machine,
now you can do another
more detailed statistic and ... exactly!
In the end Herman Hollerith
achieved his goal! At the 1890 census
the evaluation time was
reduced from ten to just two years.
To achieve this, 500 of his punches
were used to transfer the
the questionnaires
to 62 million punch cards
and then about 90
counting systems dealt with
finally evaluating them.
Last but not least,
with that the new era of
electromechanical data processing began.
A real milestone in IT history!
We thank our lecturer
Heinz Graichen
who together with his companions
in over 2000 working hours
built the statistics piano. By the way,
worldwide
there should be only two
of the originals left!
Thank you for your attention
and goodbye!